Louise Bates Ames Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- 1987 Addition, 1941-1986 (Box 41-42)
  Arranged by subject file, correspondence, writings file, and miscellany and alphabetically thereunder by name of person, subject, title, or type of material.
  - Subject file (Box 41)
    - Dream diaries, 1941-1984, (4 folders)
  - Correspondence
    - Babcock, Katherine Bradbury, 1974-1977
    - Haber, Carol Chase (granddaughter), 1959-1985, (3 folders)
    - Harper & Row, Publishers, 1979-1986 (Box 42)
    - Métraux, Ruth W. and Guy S., 1982-1986
    - Miscellany, 1966-1986, (3 folders)
    - Stone, Warren, 1970-1986
    - Treadwell, Peter, 1949-1983, (2 folders)
  - Writings file
    - "A Day with Margaret Mead"
    - "Dreams of Pregnancy"
    - "Every Child Develops at His Own Rate," chapter from The Experts Speak
    - "What Am I Doing in This Grade?"
    - "What Do They Mean I'm Difficult?"
  - Miscellany
    - Biographical and genealogical file, 1982-1986
    - Gesell Institute of Human Development, New Haven, Conn., history, 1983, undated
    - Lecture schedule, 1983-1985
- 1988 Addition, 1941-1988 (Box 43-44)
  Correspondence with family, friends, colleagues, and publishers.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Also includes Ames's Parents Ask newspaper column, 1986-1988.
  - Ames, Smith Whittier (husband), 1941-1988, undated (Box 43)
  - Armstrong, Thomas, 1984-1987
  - Buch, Mary, 1985-1987
  - Dickinson, Alice, 1977-1984
  - Ertel, Paul Y., 1978-1986, undated
  - Gesell Portrait Fund, 1950
  - Harper & Row, Publishers, regarding Youth: The Years from Ten to Sixteen, 1979-1986
  - Ilg, Frances Lillian, memorial fund, 1981
  - Perticone, Eugene X., and Renée M. Tembeckjian, 1985-1987
  - Scharbert, Beatrice, 1975-1983, undated
  - Shiff, Eileen, 1984-1988
  - Webb, Rachel, 1949-1960, (2 folders) (Box 44)
  - Miscellany, 1981-1987
  - Parents Ask newspaper column, 1986-1988
- 1996 Addition, circa 1945-1996 (Box 45-52)
  Correspondence, biographical information, dream diaries, family history, fan letters, interviews, photographs, reminiscences, and writings.
  Arranged by family correspondence, general correspondence, subject file, and writings and alphabetically thereunder by name of person, subject, title, or type of material.
  - Family correspondence (Box 45)
    - Bates, Silas and Kay (brother and sister-in-law), 1987-1995
    - Chase, Clifford (grandson), 1974-1996, undated, (10 folders)
    - Chase, Joan Ames (daughter), 1952-1973
    - Haber, Carol Chase (granddaughter), 1985-1995, (5 folders) (Box 46)
  - General correspondence
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1974-1994
    - Barry, Laurel D., 1989-1992
    - "B-C" miscellaneous, 1974-1995, undated
    - Dodson, Fitzhugh, 1977-1978
    - "D-E" miscellaneous, 1970-1995
    - Fagan, Tom, 1983
    - "F" miscellaneous, 1970-1991
    - Gillespie, Clyde, 1994
    - Gold, Svrea J., 1986-1990
    - "G" miscellaneous, 1959-1993
    - Heimgartner, Norm, 1989-1995 (Box 47)
    - Homberger, Freddy, 1978-1995, undated
    - "H" miscellaneous, 1976-1991
    - Institutes for the Achievement of Human Potential, 1967-1993
    - "I-L" miscellaneous, 1977-1996
    - Métraux, Ruth W. and Guy S., 1986-1996, (2 folders)
    - "M-O" miscellaneous, 1970-1993, undated
    - Perris, Donald L., 1960-1995, (5 folders)
    - "P" miscellaneous, 1970-1987
    - Rimland, Bernard, 1978-1989 (Box 48)
    - "R" miscellaneous, 1948-1993
    - Senn, Milton J. E., 1948-1957
    - "S" miscellaneous, 1973-1995
    - Tembeckjian, Renée M., 1988-1990
    - Treadwell, Peter and Licie, 1985-1987
    - "T-V" miscellaneous, 1970-1991
    - Webb, Rachel
      - 1960-1986, (5 folders)
      - 1987-1995, undated, (3 folders) (Box 49)
    - Wozniak, Robert H., 1984-1989
    - "W" miscellaneous, 1977-1992, undated
    - Zigler, Edward, 1988-1992
  - Subject file
    - Biographical information, 1966-1993 See also Container 52, Articles, 1993
    - Child Behavior newspaper column, 1956, undated
    - Department of Health Services, Hartford, Conn., expiration of psychologist's license, 1984-1986
    - Dream diaries, 1984-1993, (2 folders)
    - European trips, 1949-1981
    - Family history, undated
    - Fan letters, 1952-1991, undated, (2 folders) (Box 50)
    - Gesell, Arnold
      - Evaluation of Gesell's work by Ames, 1973-1974
      - Writings on Gesell by others, 1987-1993, undated, (2 folders)
    - Gesell Institute of Child Development, New Haven, Conn.
      - Board of directors, 1964-1977
      - Grants and gifts, 1952-1970
    - Gesell Institute of Human Development, New Haven, Conn.
      - Board of directors, 1978-1980
      - Privately-printed history by Ames, 1994
      - Update newsletter, 1980-1986
      - Yale University, New Haven, Conn., 1990-1993
    - Harper & Row, Publishers, 1958-1986
    - Ilg, Frances Lillian, files (Box 51)
      - Annual reports, 1962-1968
      - General correspondence, circa 1945-1980
      - Laramore, Joyce, regarding Ilg biography, 1976
      - Pilpel, Harriet F., attorney for the Gesell Institute of Child Development, New Haven, Conn., 1952-1966
      - Proposed consultation with architectural firm, 1951-1952
    - Instituto Psicopedagogico "Gesell," Maracaibo, Venezuela, 1962, 1981
    - Interviews, 1980-1989
    - Parents' Magazine, 1953
    - Photographs, 1953-1987
    - Reminiscences re
      - Associations with notable people, undated
      - Books written with Frances Lillian Ilg, undated
    - Requests for commentary on books, 1977-1994, (2 folders)
    - Research proposed but not undertaken, 1951-1954
  - Writings
    - Articles
      - 1971-1991, (2 folders)
      - 1993-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 52)
    - Books
      - Reviews, 1970, 1992
      - Your One [Two] [Three] [Four] Year Old series
        - Correspondence, 1974-1989
        - Pamphlet layout, undated
    - Introductions and prefaces, 1959-1988